Guide to the New York University Department of History Oral History Class Collection OH.033
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Lower East Side Oral History Project Interviews, 1991-1994; 7 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 4 media boxes, and 8 card catalog drawers; 0.75 Linear Feet in one record carton; 4 videocassettes (hi8); 4 videodiscs (dvd); 192 sound discs (cd); 133 audiocassettes
  - Miller, Arlene, 1994 March 18; 478466 (Box 14, Cassette 99, Box 1, Folder 67, Box 5, Cd 39)
    Arlene Miller was born in 1934 in New York, New York and grew up in an apartment on West 86th Street. Miller's parents were both born and raised in New York City. Her father was born in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. As a teenager, her father worked in an uniform factory in Baltimore, Maryland before returning to New York City and marrying. After he married, he managed his father-in-law's real estate business. In 1961, Miller opened her first business, a sweater shop, on Orchard Street in the Lower East Side. At the time of the interview, Miller owned and managed the entire building where her sweater shop was located.
    This interview was conducted on March 18, 1994 by Karen Baker at Arlene Miller's sweater store, Ja Mil Uniforms at 92 Orchard Street, Manhattan, New York. The majority of the interview covers Miller's sweater store in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. Miller discusses her store and her opinion that Ja Mil was the first store on Orchard Street to modernize its storefront display windows. She notes that the Lower East Side has undergone various changes over the years with regards to immigrant populations and types of businesses in the area.
    Duration: 28:21.
  - Miller, Mitch, 1992 October 31; 478480 (Box 15, Cassette 113A-113B, Box 1, Folder 68, Box 6, Cd 15-16)
    Mitch Miller was an anarchist and conducted extensive research on anarchism in the Lower East Side Neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and in Europe.
    This interview was conducted on October 31, 1992 by Christine Halvorson at the Muste Building, headquarters of the War Resisters' League, in Manhattan, New York. The majority of this interview covers Mitch Miller's research on twentieth century anarchism in New York, specifically in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, as well as in Europe. He discusses the decline of the Yiddish language, the Spanish Civil War, and compares anarchism in the period between the 1950s and 1970s to politics in the United States (US) at the time of the interview. Miller describes the Lower East Side to be located below Fourteenth Street and East of Second Avenue. He references the book, Fragments, written by Sam Dolgoff throughout his interview and relates that Dolgoff played an active role in the anarchist movement during the twentieth century in the Lower East Side (LES). Miller explains the tension between various ethnic groups in the LES, including gang fights between Jewish, Irish, and Italian residents and relates his opinion that between 1900 and 1940 neighborhoods were the center of people's lives.
    Duration: 2:05:00
    Anarchism -- New York (State) -- New York.
  - Morales, Carmine, 1994 February 23; 478467 (Box 1, Folder 69, Box 14, Cassette 100, Box 5, Cd 40)
    Carmine Morales was born in 1951 in New York and lived in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. He had two brothers. His father migrated to the United States from Puerto Rico after World War II, and his mother was of Italian descent and was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Morales attended Public School 42 and Seward Park High School in the LES. He married in 1979 and his wife worked at the Educational Alliance in the LES. Morales owned the Classic Coffee Shop in the LES.
    This interview was conducted on February 23, 1994 by Kerrie C. Cotton at the Classic Coffee Shop in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Carmine Morales's family and his working life. Morales discusses his parents and his paternal grandfather's disapproval of their marriage. He recounts the schools he attended, after school jobs he had, social activities in which he participated, and the ethnic demographics of the LES. He recounts working at a summer camp at Bear Mountain in New York managed by the Educational Alliance and meeting his wife there. He discusses working in restaurants in New York, before taking over the Classic Coffee Shop in the LES from his father. Morales describes the differences in the neighborhood around his coffee shop between when his father owned and at the time of the interview, as well as his customers and the food he serves.
    Duration: 57:55
  - Muse, Edward, 1993 August 9; 478438 (Box 1, Folder 70, Box 13, Cassette 71A-71B, Box 5, Cd 4-5)
    Edward Muse was born in 1921 in Danville, Virginia and was one of seven children. His mother worked as a teacher before her children were born. His father was a railway clerk for the United States Postal Service and established the first bank for African-Americans in Virginia in 1921. Muse migrated to New York in 1938 and settled in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and lived in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan between 1948 and 1954. He served in the United States Army during World War II before attending Columbia University. He worked at the WMCA radio station in New York, at the Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society, and as a staff director for the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.
    These interviews were conducted on August 9 and August 10, 1993 by Goldie Gold at Edward Muse's apartment in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Muse's childhood, family, his education, and his working life. Muse recounts his childhood in Danville, Virginia, including his parents' occupations, his mother's education, and the importance his parents placed on community and education. He discusses the sense of community amongst African-Americans in Danville and his mother's participation in the Order of the Eastern Star lodge in his hometown. Muse discusses his participation in the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), including his first interactions with the organization as a teenager, his opinions on legal successes of the organization, and the effect these events had on him. He recounts his time in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, including the apartment in which he lived, his neighbors, and the stores at which he shopped. He discusses his studies with Paul Lazarsfeld in the Bureau of Applied Social Research at Columbia University and a research study Muse conducted on intercultural relations in the LES. He recounts his work for the Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society (HIAS) and his adoption of HIAS's fundraising strategy when he worked at the NAACP.
    Duration: 2:16:10
  - Nussenblatt, Lorraine Cohen, 1991 October 18; 478404 (Box 1, Folder 71, Box 12, Cassette 34, Box 4, Cd 5)
    Lorraine Cohen Nussenblatt was born in the early 1920s in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she was one of three children. Her father immigrated to the United States (US) from Austria and worked as a baker. He died when Nussenblatt was five years old. Her mother immigrated to the US from the Latvia region of Russia, and worked as a seamstress after the death of her husband. Nussenblatt lived in the LES between the early 1920s and 1938 and the Williamsburg Houses (known as the Ten Eyck Houses at the time) in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn between 1938 and 1940. She lived in the Vladeck Houses in the LES between 1940 and 1950 and moved to the Alfred E. Smith Houses in the LES in 1950. At the time of the interview, she lived in an unspecified cooperative building in the LES. She attended Seward Park High School in the LES. Nussenblatt worked as a receptionist in a doctors' office. She married in 1944 and had two sons.
    This interview was conducted on October 18, 1991 by Elizabeth Nichols at the Henry Street Settlement's Home Planning Workshop at the Vladeck Houses in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Lorraine Cohen Nussenblatt's family and her experiences in different housing projects in New York City. Nussenblatt recounts moving into the Vladeck Houses with her mother and two siblings in 1940 as one of the first residents. She discusses her family's reasons for moving to the Williamsburg Houses in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn and then to the Vladeck Houses, and describes the two housing projects. She discusses social activities at the Educational Alliance in the LES, including dances, Hebrew classes, and sewing classes, and states that she still attended events there at the time of the interview. She discusses her duties as an air raid warden during World War II and as an officer in the Vladeck Houses Tenants Association at the Vladeck Houses. She discusses an informal loan association provided through the Vladeck Houses Tenants Association. She discusses the activities in which she participates through the Good Companions Senior Center at the Henry Street Settlement in the LES. She discusses her parents, including their immigration to the United States, their meeting at an unspecified socialist club in New York, and her mother's struggle after her husband's death.
    Duration: 1:10:01
  - O'Malley, Nora, 1991 October 16; 478405 (Box 1, Folder 72, Box 12, Cassette 35A, Box 4, Cd 6-7)
    Nora O'Malley was born in 1907 in County Mayo, Ireland. She was one of eight children. Her father was a farmer and her mother managed the household. O'Malley immigrated to the United States in 1933. She lived and worked as a cook at the Henry Street Settlement between 1933 and 1972. In 1972, she became the full-time caregiver for her niece and nephew after the death of their parents.
    This interview was conducted on October 11 and October 16, 1991 by Joseph Glancey, Jr. at an unspecified location. The interview covers Nora O'Malley's childhood in Ireland, her family, and her experiences as a cook at the Henry Street Settlement in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. O'Malley can sometimes be hard to hear. She describes her family and her childhood in Ireland, including her house and chores, her siblings, and her relationship with her parents. She recalls social and leisure activities in the village near her family's farm and Christmas and birthday traditions. She discusses the differences in cooking when she first came to the Henry Street Settlement in the 1930s and later in her career, specifically having machines to assist in peeling and cutting vegetables and frozen foods. She recounts different apartments in which she lived in the LES before she moved into 267 Henry Street, one of the buildings managed by the Henry Street Settlement, and describes her apartment. She describes the other cooks with whom she worked, their responsibilities, and types of meals they cooked. Other topics include Helen Hall and Thanksgiving at the Henry Street Settlement. See also: Beck, Bertram; Gold, Leona; McGee-Robinson, Audrey Peters
    Duration: 1:53:07
  - Opalsky, Esther, 1992 October 27; 478563 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    Esther Opalsky was born into a Jewish family in Odessa, Russia in 1911. She immigrated to Palestine from Russia in 1926 and to the United States in 1929, settling in Manhattan, New York. At the time of the interview she lived in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She married and had at least two children before divorcing her husband.
    This interview was conducted on October 27, 1992 by Helen Selsdon at the Educational Alliance in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The audio recording for this interview is missing. The interview covers Esther Opalsky's early life in Russia, her immigration experiences, and her family. Opalsky discusses her memories of Odessa, Russia and Palestine. She discusses her relationship with her husband and their divorce. She describes giving birth in Beth Israel Hospital in Manhattan. She discusses the deaths and burials of her parents.
  - Pasternak, Charles, 1993 May 12; 478439 (Box 13, Cassette 72A-72B, Box 12, Cassette 42, Box 1, Folder 74, Box 5, Cd 6-7)
    Charles Pasternak was born in 1919 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His family was Jewish and he had four siblings. His parents immigrated to the United States from Austria-Hungary in 1911. His father worked in a laundry. His mother managed the household and worked as a janitor in one of the buildings in which the family lived. Pasternak attended the Rabbi Jacob Joseph Yeshiva and Public Schools 188 and 97 in the LES. He attended Seward Park High School. He worked as a fruit seller, as a laundry worker, and as a waiter in the Catskills region of New York. He married and had two children.
    This interview was conducted on May 12, 1993 by Doris Charrow in Queens, New York. The interview covers Charles Pasternak's life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and his family. Throughout the interview Pasternak relates anecdotes and memories of his childhood and early life in the LES. He discusses his education and schools he attended in the LES. He discusses his parents, including their immigration experiences and their working lives. He describes the apartments in which his family lived in the LES, the living arrangements, and the layout. He recalls extended family members living with his family when they first arrived in the United States. He discusses jobs he held in the LES and in hotels in the Catskills region of New York. He discusses his relationship with his father and his work in the laundry with his father. He describes fires on the LES, in particular the bonfires held on election nights. He recalls a hospital ship that would dock on the East River and hold events and provide healthcare for the residents of the LES. Other topics include medical care in the LES in the 1920s and 1930s, anti-Semitism in the LES, Meyer Lansky and organized crime, and Julius and Ethel Rosenberg.
    Duration: 2:11:01
  - Pearl, Helen, 1994 February 21; 478483 (Box 1, Folder 75, Box 15, Cassette 119A-119B, Box 6, Cd 19-20)
    Helen Pearl was born in 1904 to a Jewish family in a small town in Romania. After her parents divorced, Pearl, her sister, and her mother lived with her maternal grandfather. Her mother worked as a peddler, selling household goods. Pearl went to live with her uncle in a neighboring town in Romania, because her mother was unable to financially support the family. In her early 20s, Pearl married Shortly after getting married, her husband immigrated to the United States and sent for Pearl in 1928. They lived in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York until 1939.
    This interview was conducted on February 21, 1994 by Valerie Richmond at the Hebrew Home of the Aging in New York, New York. The majority of the interview covers Helen Pearl's early life in Romania and her lack of happiness throughout her life. Pearl recalls her mother struggling to financially support the family after her parents' divorce. She reflects negatively on her childhood, the time during which she lived with her uncle, and her lack of education. Pearl explains that she married her husband not for love, but to start a family. Throughout the interview, Pearl is extremely emotional and expresses great sadness about her life as a whole. She recalls finding it difficult to work in addition to raising her children. Pearl describes finding comfort with the Jewish population in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan and missing that sense of community when she moved to the Red Hook neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    Duration: 2:03:53
  - Platin, Fanny, 1992 December 1; 478386 (Box 1, Folder 76, Box 11, Cassette 16, Box 3, Cd 24)
    Fanny Platin was born in 1913, one of seven children in a Jewish family. Her parents had immigrated to the United States from Poland. Platin was born in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She worked at the Henry Street Settlement in Manhattan for 13 years as the secretary for both the departments of the Neighborhood Worker and the Director of Adult Activities.
    This interview was conducted on December 1, 1992 by Helen Selsdon at an unspecified location. Platin discusses living in a tenement on East Broadway in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York, which she remembers as being in better condition compared to other buildings in the LES. She describes moving to Knickerbocker Village in the LES. Platin discusses services provided by the Henry Street Settlement in Manhattan during the Great Depression, such as food stamp distribution, assistance with the Department of Welfare (likely a city department), and organizing boat rides for mothers and children in the summer. Platin discusses the deaths of relatives in Poland during pogroms and illnesses experienced by family members, including diabetes and tuberculosis. She talks about her sadness over the death of her maternal grandmother when she was five years old, and discusses Jewish customs and practices surrounding death. Platin discusses living in Brooklyn as a young mother and the careers of family members.
    Duration: 37:36
  - Radosh, Ida Kreichman, 1992 December 1; 478381 (Box 11, Cassette 7A-7B, Box 1, Folder 77, Box 3, Cd 13-14)
    Ida Kreichman Radosh was born into a Jewish family in 1900 near Kiev, Russia. She immigrated to the United States with her family in 1905. They settled in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her father worked as an operator in garment factories and her mother worked as a finisher in a garment factories. Radosh attended the Hebrew Technical School for Girls in Manhattan and worked as a milliner. She married in 1922. In addition to the LES, Radosh lived in the Washington Heights neighborhood of Manhattan and the Williamsburg and Brighton Beach neighborhoods of Brooklyn.
    This interview was conducted on December 1, 1992 by Sushan Chin at Ida Kreichman Radosh's apartment in the Chelsea neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Radosh's childhood, her working life, and her family. Radosh discusses her childhood in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and relations between the different ethnic groups in the neighborhood. She discusses her parents' decision to immigrate to the United States from Russia and her father's work in garment factories. She recalls the different apartments in which the family lived in Manhattan and Brooklyn. She discusses her work as a milliner and her participation in an unspecified labor union (likely the United Hatters of North America). She discusses her friendship with anarchist Clara Larsen.
    Duration: 1:18:51
  - Regina, Frank Miggs, 1993 May 13; 478440 (Box 1, Folder 78, Box 13, Cassette 73, Box 5, Cd 8)
    Frank Miggs Regina was born in 1910 on Goerck Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and was one of ten children. His parents immigrated to the United States from Italy in the late 19th century. His father was a longshoreman and his mother took in sewing and managed the household. Regina worked as a truck driver and as a drummer, and was a member of the American Federation of Musicians, Local 802. He was married.
    This interview was conducted on May 10, 1993 by Helen Goodman at Frank Miggs Regina's apartment in Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Regina's childhood and working life. Regina discusses his childhood in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York, including the apartments in which his family lived, his weekly bath at the Baruch Baths, and the distribution of chores in his family. He discusses the deaths of his brothers and their wakes held in his family's apartment. Regina recounts playing drums in a band and playing at weddings and other events. He discusses his friendship with Sammy Cahn.
    Duration: 50:12
  - Riesner, Ruth Herzfeld, 1993 May 20; 478441 (Box 1, Folder 79, Box 13, Cassette 74, Box 5, Cd 9)
    Ruth Herzfeld Riesner was born in 1916 in Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she had four siblings. Her father immigrated to the United States (US) from Poland and owned a store selling floor coverings. Her mother immigrated to the US from Ukraine, Russia and managed the household. Riesner attended Public School 63 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan and attended Erasmus High School in Brooklyn. She worked for the Jewish Alcoholic and Chemically Dependent Persons and Significant Others or JACS. She married and had at least one child.
    This interview was conducted on May 20, 1993 by Helen Goodman at an unspecified location. The interview covers Ruth Herzfeld Riesner's early life and family. Riesner recounts living near the Third Street Music School Settlement in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She describes her family's apartment in the LES and living arrangements in the apartment. She discusses her father's floor covering business and the multiple stores that he owned. She discusses her parents and her relationship with them. She discusses the work of Jewish Alcoholic and Chemically Dependent Persons and Significant Others or JACS.
    Duration: 16:05
  - Rosen, Bernard, 1992 October 4; 478382 (Box 11, Cassette 8A-8B, Box 1, Folder 80, Box 3, Cd 15)
    Bernard Rosen was born into a Jewish family in 1934 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Rosen's parents immigrated from Poland around 1920. He lived at 127 Henry Street with his parents and sisters until he was 14 years old. His grandfather owned a tailor shop on East Broadway, his father owned a grocery store, and his mother was an embroiderer at a local shop. Rosen attended a Catholic school on Henry Street until the fifth grade. After an evaluation at Bellevue Hospital Center, Rosen was accepted into the Intellectually Gifted Children Program at Public School 33 (PS33). As a young adult, he spent time at the Garden Cafeteria located in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan to engage in political discussions and to read PM Newspaper. In 1948, the Rosens moved to the Brighton Beach neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    This interview was conducted on October 4, 1992 by Sharon B. Laist at Bernard Rosen's house in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. The majority of the interview covers Rosen's childhood in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. Occasionally, Rosen's wife, Elizabeth Rosen, can be heard correcting him. Rosen recalls living in dumbbell tenement on Henry Street that had both internal plumbing and heat. He recalls living around the corner from his paternal grandparents and remembers weekend family meals at their apartment. Rosen recalls his grandmother keeping fish in the bathtub in the kitchen before cooking them. Rosen discusses his father's grocery store and it being closed by the city in order to build the Mayor Fiorello H. LaGuardia Houses. He talks about his negative experiences at Catholic school and his acceptance into the Intellectually Gifted Children Program at Public School 33 (PS33). Rosen recalls spending time at the Lower East Side Garden Cafeteria and Union Square to attend political talks and rallies.
    Duration: 51:06.
  - Rosen, Elizabeth Flynn, 1992 September 25; cuid492 (Box 1, Folder 81, Box 3, Cd 16)